we're going to talk about the way that
light
affects our body we talked about this a
little bit before
where
light coming into our eyes
affected our circadian rhythm affected
our mood but today we're going to talk
about something that actually goes way
beyond our wildest imaginations
about how
light can actually affect our well-being
so let's jump in
so as we said we talked about how humans
interact with light and we said that
there is a circadian rhythm component to
it with our eyes
today however we're going to talk about
how our skin and our body and the cells
beneath our skin and specifically a
portion
of our cells a organelle inside of our
cells
called the mitochondria
interact with light and these are the
powerhouses of the cell this is where we
make something called atp or
adenosine triphosphate this is the
energy of the cell and it's in every
single cell just about
these little tiny machines
that are making this energy and it's
important that we understand why
this is
important in terms of its interaction
with light
so again let's review a little bit here
okay so we've got the mitochondria in
the cells and again this is really
important in terms of
making energy for the cell and as a
byproduct of that energy just like an
engine makes locomotion
and makes heat and if you don't deal
with the heat it can shut down the
engine the mitochondria makes energy but
as a byproduct of that energy it also
makes something called oxidative stress
so those reactive oxygen species these
are basically oxygen molecules with
extra electrons around them that can
damage things it's like heat in the
engine and if you don't take care of
that heat in the engine or oxidative
stress in this case it's well known to
lead to less optimal health so things
like inflammation cancer dementia
diabetes even learning disabilities like
autism
have been linked to
damaged mitochondria
so as it turns out the body has a way of
mitigating or diminishing
this damage
to the mitochondria in your cells and
there's two systems that are put in
place there's a system that's put in
place at night
and there's a system that's put in place
during the day
so let's talk about at night we talked
about this the last time we got together
and there's this little gland in the
brain called the pineal gland which
makes melatonin so melatonin i want you
to think of as like the cooling system
of an engine melatonin
is secreted from the pineal gland it
goes through the blood supply it is
taken up by the cells and is transported
into the mitochondria where it cools
down the engine there it's it's a very
powerful antioxidant and it mops up
these reactive oxygen species so that it
does not cause
oxidative stress so you can see why it's
so important that you sleep at night and
that you don't expose your eyes to
bright light at night because all of
these things can interrupt melatonin if
you're not getting good melatonin
secretion at night your mitochondria are
running hot
they are there's steam coming out of the
engine as they're burning up the hill
and you're putting in overtime
and that's not good for your engine
because we know what happens to engines
when they're over stressed and burned
out they
seize and they're no longer any good and
you need good mitochondria so that's the
system at night what happens however
during the day well science
and scientists and studies are now
starting to illuminate if you will this
this topic and what they're saying is
that actually
melatonin is produced
on-site
in the mitochondria itself right where
it's needed
due to and this is the part that they're
working out still due to near infrared
radiation near-infrared radiation is a
portion of the spectrum that comes from
the sun
that you get when you're outside we'll
talk a little bit more about that but
where did this come from it comes from a
paper that was published by scott
zimmerman and russell writer titled
melatonin and the optics of the human
body this was just published back in
and this is what they said they said
that
melatonin is a potent
antioxidant molecule it's produced
within the mitochondria in response to
sunlight and provides targeted
protection of mitochondria from reactive
oxygen species that's really important
now this is the this is the hypothesis
of this paper but there are studies that
show very clearly that mitochondria
make melatonin
and so melatonin that is produced in the
mitochondria could be protective against
a range of diseases some of these
diseases sound actually very familiar
like cancer
neurodegenerative diseases like
alzheimer's disease cardiovascular
disease that's like heart attacks and
congestive heart failure and also
diabetes and it may also have a role in
prevention and treatment of alzheimer's
parkinson's
this oxidative stress
as a proposed mechanism for the beta
amyloid accumulation
and dopaminergic neuron death
and even covet 19 we're going to talk
about kova 19 and why
sunlight exposure may actually be the
key
that unlocks the mystery of why some
have higher mortality rates with coven
19.
so in this paper they showed that we
used to think that you know melatonin
was a product of the pineal gland which
it still is
but 20 times more actually come
from the mitochondria themselves they
say here quote it has now been shown
that the mitochondria produce melatonin
in many cells in quantities which are
orders of magnitude higher
than produced in the pineal gland the
subcellular melatonin does not
necessarily fluctuate with our circadian
clock or release into the circulation
system
but
instead has been proposed to be consumed
locally
in response to the free radical density
that's reactive oxygen species within
each cell in particular in response to
near infrared
radiation exposure
they go on based on an optical and
biological review of the literature it
is proposed that near infrared portion
of natural sunlight stimulates an excess
of antioxidants in each of our healthy
cells and that the cumulative effect of
this antioxidant reservoir is to enhance
the body's ability to rapidly and
locally deal with changing conditions
throughout the day
in this approach the role of the
circulatory melatonin produced by the
pineal gland is to provide an efficient
method of delivering supplemental
melatonin during periods of low cellular
activity and solar stimulus to damaged
or aging cells in both diurnal and
nocturnal animals
while circulatory melatonin may be the
hormone of darkness
subcellular melatonin may be the hormone
of daylight
so what they're saying here is that
melatonin is really the answer both at
night and during the day but the way
that you get it is in an opposite way
you have to avoid light at night to get
melatonin and you have to be outside in
the sunlight during the day to get the
very same molecule
but what exactly is near infrared
radiation well we see that light from
the sun that we can see with the visible
eye is only about 39 of the energy
that's coming from the sun
just beyond the red near infrared
spectrum is we see this area called near
infrared
and that is the area specifically that
is thought to produce
the
the substance of melatonin in the
mitochondria now notice that these
wavelengths that are very very
long past what we can see in the visible
spectrum are very good
at penetrating deep into tissues
i want you to think about it like this
you're pulling up to a stoplight and
those teenagers that are pulling up next
to you in their car blaring their very
loud music what do you hear you hear the
deep
frequencies you hear the long
wavelengths because those wavelengths
are very good at penetrating not only
their car but also your car and
vibrating the steering wheel it's the
same thing here these wavelengths can
penetrate through clothes
they can penetrate through the
atmosphere it can penetrate through your
skin and actually go fairly deep
and here's an illustration of that you
can see here that
these wavelengths which really here are
in the near infrared they penetrate down
the deepest even into the blood vessels
which we'll talk about in a little bit
and also the subcutaneous layer which
basically is the layer of fat and in
some cases there's been some studies
that have indicated that it can even
penetrate up to eight centimeters deep
think about eight centimeters deep all
around your body that this near infrared
radiation in this case it was 900
nanometers
wavelength
both in people who were melanin
deficient and melanin rich you can see
in both cases that this near infrared
radiation penetrated in fact
in nursing it's actually used to see
where the blood vessels are because the
blood vessels absorb the near infrared
light and don't reflect it so when
you're putting visible light for
instance on a hand looking for blood
vessels you really can't see it but when
you do near infrared lights at about 810
nanometers
you can see here that you can see these
blood vessels
in the hands why it's because this type
of light penetrates that deep
and so what this graph is showing you is
that if you look at the total number of
cells in the human body which is
represented by this black line over age
from 0 to 80 years of age you can see
that the cells that are exposable to
near infrared radiation is actually
quite a large number i would say 75
percent at the very least
so that's important i mean think about
that you go outside and up to 70 75
percent of your cells in your body are
getting near infrared radiation from the
sun
now there's even some evidence that your
brain
can benefit from their infrared
radiation and you're like what wait a
minute now how is it possible
that sunlight could penetrate
your hair
and your skin on your head and even your
skull how is that even possible this is
exactly what they are proposing in this
article that in fact
sunlight is able to penetrate through
the skull
hits the cerebral spinal fluid which
surrounds the brain
which acts as a diffuser and then the
near infrared radiation is reflected
down into these crevices
where it's supplants sorry where it
actually supplies near infrared
radiation to the gray matter which just
happens to be
on the outside of the brain where it can
receive the gray matter is important to
understand because gray matter is where
the cells are it's where the
mitochondria
are and it just happens to be at the
cell surface where the most amount of
surface area is and here you can
actually see
a brain
and transmission of near infrared light
you can see that it's very able to be
seen here now
again when i saw this for the first time
i was a little incredulous how is it
possible that this light can penetrate
through the skull but then i remembered
back
to medical school and we used to take
light and we would put it on the skin
and as you can see here it's lighting up
the entire frontal sinuses these are
basically cavities
inside of the skull you can see here on
a side section this area right here is
one big sinus and this area here is also
a big sign such that when you illuminate
light here on the uh on the front of the
face you can see inside the mouth light
is able to penetrate not only the skin
and the bone here through this sinus but
also illuminate the bone and the mucosa
on top of the bone here so as you can
see it's very conceivable and possible
that near infrared radiation could
penetrate through bone and as we'll see
later there may be some benefits to this
at least in some studies
now it gets even more mind-blowing
because get ready hold on to your seats
when you're outside and you're in the
sun spectrum when you're looking at the
light coming from the sun you can see
here that most of that light that you're
seeing as we talked about
the majority here is in the visible
spectrum but there is quite a bit
in the near infrared although it doesn't
seem to be as much as in terms of
intensity
however
however if you're outside and you're in
green spaces for instance trees grass
plants
these sorts of things very very
efficiently reflect near infrared
radiations and you can see here what
happens there's a huge increase in the
amount of near infrared radiation so
that by the time the light is hitting
your eyes when you're outside in green
spaces you're getting a lot more near
infrared light so the key take home here
is is that yes you need to go outside
for near infrared radiation but you're
going to get a lot more of it if you're
in areas that are surrounded by green
plants as opposed to a concrete jungle
now let me show you some examples of
that here we have a near infrared
photograph
of scent of a um of a
of a park and you can see here that the
green leaves the grass it looks like
there's snow that has just fallen on
here and it's not snow it's simply that
the intensity of near-infrared is so
great that on this near-infrared filter
it appears as though they are white
to give you a contrast here this is what
central park looks like and you can see
the buildings here are pretty much
devoid of any kind of reflection of
near-infrared radiation
but the trees here again
are reflecting a tremendous amount of
near-infrared radiation
and the question is is it possible that
people who are living in green spaces
might get more near infrared radiation
therefore
have better mitochondria because they're
making more melatonin which is better
cooling
well this may be in fact what's going on
but i can tell you we've known for quite
a long time
that the health benefits of being
outside in the great outdoors is well
documented this is a paper that was
published in environmental research
titled the health benefits of the great
outdoors a systematic review and
meta-analysis of green space exposure
and health outcomes and they said here
quote we found that spending time in or
living close to natural green spaces
is associated with a diverse and
significant health benefits it reduces
the risk of type 2 diabetes
cardiovascular disease premature death
and preterm birth and increases sleep
duration people living closer to nature
also had reduced diastolic blood
pressure heart rate and stress in fact
one of the really interesting things we
found is that exposure to green space
significantly reduces people's levels of
salivary cortisol a physiological marker
of stress
so what we're seeing here is we know the
data we know that people live better
lives when they're outside what's really
interesting about this new research in
terms of near infrared radiation and
melatonin and mitochondria is this this
actually may represent a mechanism as to
why this is occurring
what we have here is a summary table
of a phd candidate's thesis
which is summarizing all of the benefits
of as they call it here daylighting on
students we've known for a long time in
the united states
that students really do benefit from
natural light in fact there are codes
that have been put in place specifically
for school and educational buildings
that dictate how big the windows have to
be and the reason is is because they've
known for a long time that natural light
in educational buildings is extremely
important well as you can see here
things that have been improved like
health vitamin d
students vision calcium absorption bone
formation biological clock all of these
are benefited with light we talked about
this last time with mood
student attendance and sleep being
improved with natural light but you may
not know this that learning achievement
learning math school attendance and even
test scores
have been shown to be improved with
light is it possible that near infrared
radiation from the sun is penetrating
the skull and is giving that gray matter
the energy and the cooling system for
its mitochondria that it needs to
perform
it certainly is possible i think in fact
likely
what about reduce we know that headaches
are reduced cancer stomach ulcers high
blood pressure stress
microbes depression fatigue
sad or seasonal affective disorder we
talked about that last time violent
behavior stress
and improved security
so you need less security guards when
you have natural light all of these
things have been shown to be improved
now what is interesting is now we're
starting to see why
this might be the case
what about some more data on this here's
a article that was published in clinical
endocrinology titled shining the light
on sunshine a systematic review of the
influence of sun exposure on type 2
diabetes mellitus related outcomes and
what they did there is they looked at
observational studies and they looked to
see what would happen if you compared
sun exposure and the incidence
of type 2 diabetes and what they showed
there is that there was a moderate level
of quality of evidence that showed that
there was
outcomes of type 2 diabetes that went
down with increased sun exposure there
was another study that was published
this one titled associations of outdoor
temperature bright sunlight and
cardiometabolic traits in two european
population-based cohorts one of these
was in oxfordshire that's the hometown
of oxford university and the other one
was in the netherlands
in leiden netherlands and what they did
was a really interesting study they had
people uh about 7 000 in the uk and
about 6 600 in the netherlands go to
give blood tests and these blood tests
looked at everything like di over
diabetes cardiovascular
and lipids hypercholesterolemia
hypertriglyceridemy all of these tests
and what they did was they used weather
reports
in these two cities and they gathered
all the data and they wanted to see how
many days of sunlight were there in the
seven previous days
to when somebody randomly gave
their
blood sample so they looked at all these
blood samples and they looked back to
see how much sun were they exposed to in
just the last seven days so first of all
realize that we're looking at the effect
of sunlight over a seven day period of
time that's pretty strong pretty
powerful pretty short term and what did
they find they found in in all of these
situations that not only with respect to
glucose metabolism but also lipid
metabolism that there was an association
that the more sun there was
in the past seven days the better
overall were the indices in the blood
samples that they received from these
two european countries
but you might be saying dr schwell but i
was told that you really should not go
out into the sun there's damaging
ultraviolet
radiation that could give you skin
cancer and could burn you and cause
problems later on down the road and that
is certainly
true in a sense and here what we're
looking at here is the amount of
radii
radioactive if you will radicals that
get produced
with the different types of radiation
you can see here in the visible spectrum
and even far beyond in the near infrared
that there's very little
in terms of ionizing radiation the bulk
of ionizing radiation
is happening here in the ultraviolet a
spectrum and the ultraviolet b spectrum
and you should know that this type of
radiation really is bountiful between
about 10 a.m in the morning to about 2
p.m in the afternoon that's where you're
going to see the most of that type of
radiation also you should know that
whereas this type of radiation over here
near infrared radiation can very easily
penetrate clothes
okay it penetrates clothes
this type of radiation does not
so what i would say is that if you
wanted to get plenty of near infrared
radiation and avoid
ultraviolet radiation i would avoid
going out into the sun between ten and
two and if you have to you could always
make sure you layer on clothes
so that you don't get exposed to too
much ultraviolet radiation however
there's a caveat there and i would say
this that ultraviolet b radiation which
is right here
is the source
of vitamin d
or i should say is a source of vitamin d
if you don't get ultraviolet b radiation
you're not going to make vitamin d and
i'll tell you if you are wearing too
many clothes
you will not get vitamin d if you're
inside it will not penetrate through the
window so it's it's easy to become
vitamin d deficient that's why i
recommend supplementing with vitamin d
but realize as we've just shown here
that just because you supplement with
vitamin d that is no excuse for
not going outside that is not a
substitute for getting sunlight
but you may be surprised to to say well
what happens to these people that tend
to go out into the sun here's a paper
that was published called sun exposure
and mortality
from melanoma and what did they find
they found that
behaviors that were associated with a
decrease in death
was
high intermittent sun exposure and even
sunburn
or even solar elastosis what is solar
elastosis it's basically the sign of
sun damage on the skin they found that
those people that actually had evidence
of sunlight exposure on their skin had a
decreased death rate compared to those
that did not
here's another paper that was published
in the journal of internal medicine
titled avoidance of sun exposure is a
risk factor for all cause mortality the
results of the melanoma in southern
sweden cohort this is a huge study 30
000 women in southern sweden so these
are pretty fair-skinned people generally
and these are not old 35 to 64.
and they were followed prospectively for
20 years so this is a really good
design study
and what they found was that there were
you know
unavoidably there were about 2 500
deaths over the 20 years
that
they followed them and they asked about
all sorts of things including sun
exposure risk sunbathing tanning salons
etc well what do you think they found
they found that those
people that avoided the sun
that's the solid line here these are sun
avoiding people they had less mean
survival and that those people that were
out in the sun
in southern sweden fair-skinned people
they had
higher survival these people here were
up here
whereas the people that avoided the sun
were down there so you can see here and
as the time went on the difference
became bigger and bigger and bigger
okay so a little while ago we talked
about how
near infrared radiation actually could
benefit
people outside of maybe even their gray
matter in their brains or even the total
weight of their brain i thought it was
interesting study look at this when we
took people with multiple sclerosis
and we looked at those that had the
lowest amount of sunshine and the
highest amount of sunshine in all of
these cases
they had higher gray matter volume and
higher
whole brain volume
the same sort of thing we saw in the
control groups the people that had the
least amount of sunshine had the lower
gray matter volume and those that had
the highest amounts had the highest gray
matter volume
similarly also we saw that in controls
although the the difference was really
pronounced
in people with multiple sclerosis
remember that multiple sclerosis is seen
predominantly
generally in higher latitudes that means
people higher up more north
okay what about covet 19 so we know that
every year we always have a peak in
influenza in the winter months it's
almost like clockwork and you can see it
here very clearly in the winter of all
of these years there's always a peak
sometimes it's higher than others
and the question is is what's causing
this
and so there was a group that went out
to look at this because the same thing
was being seen with covet 19 as well and
so this group
published this report in scientific
reports titled autumn cove at 19 surge
dates in europe correlate to latitudes
not to temperature humidity pointing to
vitamin d as a contributing factor well
what we'll see about that
here's what they found
so when they looked at
the
time of the year the time in the winter
time that european countries had their
inflation
of cases
what they found was something that was
really interesting they wanted to know
whether or not it correlated with the
temperature so people said well you know
it gets cold and this is the reason why
people's immune systems don't work and
therefore that's when we would start to
see the surge in coven 19 cases and as
you can see flat line meaning no
correlation so temperature had nothing
to do with it
and some people said no it's the
humidity humidity is what's causing it
to transmit and that's the reason why
well guess what correlation flat line
no
correlation whatsoever however when they
started to look at latitude in other
words
countries in europe that were the
farthest north
seem to get the first inflation rates of
coven you can see here finland here at
the bottom which is pretty high north
and it just went down the line until
finally it ended up the last country to
get it was greece and as we all know
greece is there in southern europe and
so it worked very well i mean it was a
perfect correlation just about
that latitude
was what determined when the country
got its inflation rates and of course
what's involved with latitude it's sun
exposure obviously the further north you
are in the winter time the less
sunlight you're going to get
so the question is is is that sunlight
helping in some respect
against reactive oxygen species or
against
this dysfunction this mitochondrial
dysfunction well let's let's look at
that and see if that's the case so to do
that we have to get down to a little bit
of biochemistry
now
we're gonna get a little technical but
stick with me on this it's all about
oxidative stress
there is a substance in your body called
angiotensin ii or at2 which is a
pro-oxidant it's in your cells and it's
not good for your cells it tips your
cells too much over to the pro-oxidant
side
and so it can be converted into a
substance called
angiotensin 1-7 which actually turns out
to be an antioxidant so it's actually
the flip side of that molecule
it actually can turn into something
being pro oxidant into pro antioxidant
well as it turns out the enzyme that
does this is a very important enzyme
because it's called ace2 now ace2 as you
may recall is the receptor for the sars
cov2virus
so when you have the virus floating
around your body it binds the ac2 with
the spike protein
it takes the ace2 enzyme out of
commission so now what happens is that
there's a huge buildup of angiotensin ii
because it's not being converted to
angiotensin 1 7 and you get an increase
in reactive oxygen species
that is not
good
that's like your engine
uh revving and now you're going up a
hill and so you may not have been
running the engine cool before but now
you have a coven 19 infection you're now
going up the hill
consequently your
angiotensin 1 7 is not being made and so
as a result of that that's also
contributing to high reactive oxygen
species not only that but when you get
the virus binding the ace2 that shuts
that down it also recruits white blood
cells which have even more reactive
oxygen species
so you can see here is that a covalent
19 infection is going to greatly
whack out of balance your oxidative
balance in all of your cells that this
virus infects and as it infects more and
more cells more and more cells start to
get more and more oxidized and damaged
and that can cause blood clots and
hypoxemia especially if it's in the
lungs and guess where stars kobe 2
starts out it starts out in the lungs
so how do you reduce reactive oxygen
species again through melatonin that's
why you need to get good night's sleep
that's why as we said you need to be in
bed early you need to shut down the
lights so melatonin can do its job
that's why it's so important to get
sleep in fact
recently the american academy of
cardiology has added sleep to one of
those things that you can do to prevent
cardiovascular disease and this is the
reason why
what russell rider and scott zimmerman
are promoting and
proposing
is that
sunshine during the day is making
melatonin through near-infrared
radiation and that's going to drop down
in a big way this reactive oxygen
species and may be beneficial
so i'm not just saying this
out of thin air there's evidence to this
so a number of studies this is one of
those studies looked at 60 patients and
what did they find
they found that in terms of antioxidants
in the human body
that in the control groups notice what
happens to antioxidants in the human
body as you get older it goes down
notice in every single one of these age
groups if you get infected with covid
there's a reduction
in
the antioxidants in your human body look
at this what about
the amount of oxidative stress in
control groups you can see that as you
get older there's a huge rise especially
in the 60 plus year old group that
oxidative stress goes up notice what
happens in covet infections each one of
those groups it's even higher
what about oxidative damage so things
that get destroyed damaged the
mitochondria isn't working look in the
control groups as you get older
oxidative damage goes up and in every
one of these age groups that have
coveted it's even higher than that
so could this all be vitamin d we just
need to take vitamin d because we get
vitamin d from the sun
well we know that vitamin d
is associated with better outcomes so
here's here's a study that looks at it
really well i mean in terms of inpatient
survival of people hospitalized with
cova 19 those that had good vitamin d
levels had better survival than those
that had bad vitamin d levels
and you can see that in multiple studies
so what scientists want to do is to
figure out is this really true is is
vitamin d really what's going on or
could it be something else in the
sunlight like for instance near infrared
radiation that might be doing it so they
did an interesting study they looked at
three countries and first they looked at
the united states in the wintertime
okay in the winter time this is
important to understand what they did
was they they eliminated the portion of
the country
where you could actually get vitamin d
from the winter sun because remember in
the winter time the sun is pretty low in
the sky vitamin d comes from ultraviolet
b radiation which cannot penetrate very
well through the atmosphere and so these
people that are living up here in high
latitudes they're still getting sunshine
but they're not getting enough
ultraviolet b radiation
to get and make vitamin d so the
question was was there an increase in
survival
as you went down
in latitude
despite the fact that you weren't
getting any vitamin d and the answer was
yes as you got more and more sunlight
notice what happened to mortality it
dropped despite the fact that vitamin d
wasn't even involved
and then when they saw that they said
okay let's look at england and see if
that works of course they didn't have to
to
scratch out any areas in england because
england is so far north that you can't
get enough vitamin d in the winter time
anywhere in england
nevertheless what did they find
as
sunshine amounts went up as you went
lower down in latitude
guess what
mortality went down they also repeated
again in italy
again more sunshine even though you're
not making vitamin d
went with
less mortality
fascinating in fact the authors said in
conclusion this study is observational
therefore
any causal interpretation needs to be
taken with caution however
if the relationship identifies proves to
be causal it suggests that optimizing
sun exposure may be a public health
intervention given the fact
that in effect appears to be independent
of vitamin d pathway it suggests
possible
new
cova 19
therapies
like maybe near-infrared radiation like
maybe even sunlight
and in fact
folks this is not new at all in fact if
you look back 100 150 years
we knew this
we may have forgotten it but our
ancestors knew that if you were sick if
you were in a hospital one of the best
things that you could do was to get
outside and get some sunshine you can
see it here in these black and white
photographs from the uk from the united
states
they made it a point look i i had a
friend who was a neurosurgeon she said
that in seattle
they had a solarium in their hospital
solarium was where the patients would go
in the wintertime to be under the glass
to get a lot of sun and in the summer
time the glass was removable they could
get direct sunlight
for this
you know there was a health reformer at
the time in 1871 who said this
quote the feeble one should press out
into the sunshine as earnestly and
naturally as do the shaded plants and
vines the pale and sickly grain blade
that has struggled up out of the cold of
early spring puts out the natural and
healthy deep green after enjoying for a
few days the health and life-giving rays
of the sun
go out into the light and warmth of the
glorious sun you pale and sickly once
and share with vegetation its
life-giving health-dealing power that
was published in the health reformer may
1st
and to boot she also said this
make it a habit not to sit up after nine
o'clock every light should be
extinguished this turning night of the
day is a wretched health destroying
habit
and you know folks things have changed
in the last hundred years
here
on the left we see a near infrared
picture of a summer day in a wheat field
this is what it used to look like it's
what we used to see when we're out there
in the harvesting fields in the daylight
hours getting that near infrared
radiation here on the right it's
completely black because
our led bulbs and our low e glass
prevent very effectively any
near-infrared radiation from coming into
our offices
our schools and our homes in fact if you
look at what's happened over the last
200 years
here in red we see the amount of near
infrared slowly but surely diminishing
down to a
minuscule amount i mean we used to spend
about 50 percent of our time outdoors in
the 1800s now we're about 7 percent
outdoors we need to get outdoors also
today we have led bulbs which emit no
near infrared radiation and low e glass
windows so let's take a look at that
here we see
in this orange this is the solar
radiation spectrum you can see that
there is plenty of near infrared
radiation that's coming off of the sun
we have the incandescent bulb which did
a generally good job of giving us near
infrared radiation as you can see right
here
but when we change those bulbs to led
which you know for good reason we don't
want to waste energy
on lights because energy is an issue in
this country but realize the price that
we're paying is that we're not getting
any near infrared radiation from those
bulbs
what about glass well if you have glass
in your house or building from more than
50 years ago the chances are that you've
got regular glass and you are
having a great time transmitting
near-infrared radiation into your home
however if you put low e-glass in there
you can see that
high solar gain low e-class moderate
solar gain
low e-glass and low solar gain low
e-glass
is really dropping down the amount of
near-infrared radiation that is coming
through and so what we have
let's put it all together if we were to
look
at a campfire of 200 years ago at night
notice it is dark notice that the light
is low down in the visual spectrum
notice that is in the orange to red hues
and so this is the type of light that we
would not expect to greatly reduce
melatonin production at night
however this is the reality this is what
we have today
and it's a very different picture and we
can see that that is not the optimal
approach
what we see here in nature
is we see that near infrared photons
start to increase towards noon and as
the day goes down it starts to come down
if we look at ultraviolet light it peaks
typically between 10 and 2 and then goes
back down again and we see that free
radicals are here and that are taken
care of by
melatonin and the near infrared photons
that are produced up here
when we're inside we're not getting any
of those near infrared photons we are
getting some ultraviolet light from the
incandesce or sorry from the ultraviolet
spectrum in our
fluorescent bulbs
and as a result of that we're getting
free radicals but we're not getting any
melatonin producing
near infrared radiation it's gone
so this is the reason why i say what we
need to get outside
so we've talked about
how
humans interact with light
from the eyes
sleep circadian rhythm mood and today we
talked about how it hits the
mitochondria so what should we do i
think this is what we ought to do number
one get as much
natural sunlight direct or indirect as
possible and avoid glass in between
after waking up in the morning so that
means get up in the morning
get outside
let that near infrared radiation hit you
let that light come into your eyes and
do what it needs to do
number two
exposure to low level red light like
fire sunset at sense of time is
advisable and avoid any type of light
exposure after sunset especially blue
light and especially one to two hours
prior to bedtime
so you can see that light is really
amazing and specifically light
coming from the sun now so what are some
questions what kind of clothes should
you wear you can go outside look you can
go outside and you can cover your body
so that you're not getting ultraviolet
radiation especially if you're concerned
about getting melanomas or getting skin
cancer
put some put some sunscreen on if you
want even because near infrared
radiation which is the type of radiation
that they believe produces melatonin
will penetrate through clothes
it will penetrate through sunscreen it
will penetrate through your broad rim
hat it'll even penetrate through your
umbrella what it is it's that feeling of
warmth look if you've got that t-shirt
on and you turn with your back to the
sun
you'll still feel the warmth of the sun
that warmth that you're feeling is
actually specifically near infrared
radiation penetrating through your shirt
going deep into your skin and activating
the heat receptors deep down in your
skin
folks that's the best way of getting the
most amount of melatonin it's much
better to get that type of melatonin
than to take a supplement the supplement
usually is way overdosed
it's going to make you feel sleepy it's
going to go into your bloodstream this
type of melatonin that gets produced
from the sun is not being produced in
your blood it's being produced in your
cells in fact in your mitochondria
that's what's proposed by these two
scientists that publish the paper
so again
if you can
get outside we spend far too much time
inside our homes
inside our cars inside our work and
we're not getting enough outside get
into the shade just get outside
and you will benefit from the from the
natural healing rays
of the sun
and i think this is really important now
as at least to the northern hemisphere
we're starting to see that the days are
getting shorter and we're headed toward
december when we have our shortest day
of the year it's going to be even more
important as we expect to see an
increase in coven 19 cases and other
viral cases that we're going to need to
have a good innate immune system to
battle these types of viruses and for
that i would expect that getting out and
getting good amounts of sunshine and
good rest
is going to be very important so if you
have got questions
please put those in the chat you can
also email us
we hope that you have a very blessed
week and thank you for joining us